你好黑客
hello hackers
欢迎来到PWN学院的新模块
welcome to a new module in pwn college
我很高兴今天能和大家讨论动态分配器误用
i'm very excited to talk to you today about dynamic allocator misuse
介绍堆是什么
with the introductory lecture about what the heap is
你们可能听过我在课上用堆这个词
you probably heard me use the term heap just kind of casually throughout the course
我们将深入讲解它
we're gonna dive into the vary cracks of it
首先有几点要介绍的是
so let's start from kind of something close to first principles
首先是内存的类型
first principles consider the types of memory
到目前为止，我们学过很多种内存类型
the types of memory that we've covered so far is kind of varies
我们已经讨论了elf文件的不同部分
right we've talked about different parts of an elf file
尤其是当它被加载到内存时的
especially as it's loaded into memory
text段、plt、got
the text section the plt the got
还有存放我们要用的全局变量的bss段等等
that bss where we interacted with global variables and so on
我们已经广泛地讨论过栈
we've talked about the stack pretty extensively as
在你ROP时
you have used return oriented programming
通过在栈上编写串联返回地址来实现你的目标等等
by programming return addresses onto the stack to accomplish your goals and so on
但有一种内存我们还一直没介绍过
but what we haven't really covered yet is a use case that is
一种非常常见的类型
a fairly common use case
在程序中非常常见
very common use case for programs
就是存储动态分配内存并需要较长生命周期的内存类型
which is a place to store memory that is dynamically allocated but also long lived
栈上分配内存发生在函数调用时
so the stack kind of allocates memory during the invocation of a function
或者在栈上分配内存
or memory is allocated on the stack
当涉及到函数调用时，才在栈上保留空间
space is reserved on the stack when a function is involved
但是当函数返回时
but when the function returns
该内存被释放
that memory is deallocated
但是如果你需要记录一个游戏的状态
but what if you had for example a state of a game
它记录了一系列实体，比如野怪之类的
that had a list of entities like bad guys or something
你必须持续追踪这个列表。它可能会增长，可能会缩减
that you had to track in this list. might grow might shrink
可能会有一些野怪被刷出来
there might be some baddies that spawn
可能会有一些野怪被清掉
might be some baddies that get destroyed
并且
and
这些数据需要被不同的函数访问
all of this needs to survive across invocations of many different functions well
我们可以回想一下
we can think back to the
我们接触过的内存类型
type of memory that we've interacted with and
还有一个我之前没有提到的
there's an additional one that i didn't mention previously
就是mmap申请的内存，对吧
which is a mmap memory right
我们已经看过了mmap的用法
so we have seen the use of mmap
可以根据需要申请并使用内存页
to create pages in memory on demand and interact with them right
这当然没问题
and so of course it was okay
对每个野怪、NPC、实体或对象，都没问题
no problem for every baddie for every npc for every entity or every object
对于需要在不同函数的不同调用中保持有效的数据
that we need to persist across multiple invocations of multiple functions
我们都可使用mmap
we will use mmap
来创建一个内存页
to create a page of memory
来映射一页内存
to map a page of memory
然后使用那个内存页
and then use that page of memory
当我们用完后，我们再unmap掉
and when we're done we'll unmap it
这很好
so this is great and that
它允许这种动态分配，动态释放
it allows this dynamic allocation deallocation and
并且分配的内存可在不同的函数中访问
and the allocated memory survives across different functions
这是很棒的，对吧
that's awesome right however
它有几个问题
it has problems a couple of problems
一是分配大小非常不灵活
one is the allocation size is very inflexible
它必须是4096字节的倍数
it has to be a multiple of 40 96 bytes
这是因为这就是页面的大小
so that's because that's how big a page is
而mmap只能以内存页为单位管理内存
and mmap only works on the basis of a page
另一个问题是
the other problem is that
这是一个非常慢的方法
this is a very very slow solution
内存映射、创建内存映射，取消内存映射，更改内存映射
memory mapping the creation unmapping the changing of memory maps
都要经过内核
it all has to go through the kernel
而这样速度很慢
and it had and that's slow
你必须切换到内核空间，你必须
right you have to switch into kernel space you have to
系统调用必须被处理等等
the syscall has to be handled et cetera cetera
与此相关的开销相当大
there's quite a lot of overhead associated with that
如果我们能聪明一点，我们说好的
so if we could get a little bit more clever and we say okay
不需要为每个元素都进行内存映射
but you don't need to memory map for every single element
不管它是数组元素还是某个数据结构成员
of an array of that element or of a data structure whatever
如果这个元素很小
if that element is small right
如果它只是16字节
if it's 16 bytes
我们不需要分配一个有4096字节的完整内存页
we don't have to allocate an entire page of 4096 bytes
只需要分配一个页面
they just allocate that page
然后以一个小的单位管理它
and then they'll slowly start handing of pieces right
你可以写一个库来做这个
so if you could write a library that does this
它有一个分配内存的函数
that has an allocate memory function that
如果你需要一个128字节的内存
you know if you say give me a hundred and twenty eight bytes
它会给你一个指向那块内存开头的指针
and it gives you a pointer to the beginning of that page then
并且追踪记录
and and keeps track
那128字节已经被使用
that that a hundred and twenty eight has been used
然后你又要256字节
and you say give me another 256 bytes
然后它又给你一块256字节的内存
then it'll give you the 256 bytes
然后你还会用到一些函数
and then maybe you can have some function
比如你不在需要这块内存了
for saying okay no longer need this memory
这就是一个动态分配器
and what this is is a dynamic allocator
并且已经有现成的了，这也是内存被管理的方式
and these exist this is in fact how memory is managed
我们不是第一个有这个想法的人，震惊
we're not the first to have this idea shockingly right
图为Doug lea
pictured here is Doug lea
他创造并发布了第一个
he created and released the first
公开的大众都能获得到的动态分配器
kind of very public very accessible allocator into the public domain
这很酷
so this was very cool
它不仅仅是开源的，发布在互联网上
it's kind of not just open source but it just dumped on the Internet
而且在1987年没有其它代替品
deal with this or what you will in 1987
所以这个想法一点都不新鲜
right so this idea is very much not new at all
事实上已经有三十多年了
in fact over thirty years old um
Doug Lea创建一个dlmalloc DL是Doug Lea的缩写
Doug Lea create a dlmalloc DL is Doug Lea
它已经演变成或者被fork并扩展成
um which has morphed into or or was forked and expand
顺便说一下，dlmalloc仍然存在
a dlmalloc by the way still exist
你可以去Doug Lea的网站
you can go to Doug Lea's a website
他现在是纽约的计算机科学教授
he's a uh computer science professor in New York now
嗯
um
就算在那时这张照片也已经很过时了
and i think was back then this photo is already quite dated
我尽力找了一张像是1987年的照片
i tried to find a photo back from something that looked like 1987
后来，dlmalloc被fork到Linux用户空间
later on dlmalloc was forked into the Linux userspace
被放到glibc中作为ptmalloc
are really into glibc as ptmalloc
pt代表支持Posix线程
pt stands for Posix Thread aware
它是dlmalloc的多线程实现
so it's a multi threaded implementation of dlmalloc
还有其他的malloc
and there are other mallocs and other parts of the computer world
FreeBSD有一个jemalloc
FreeBSD had something called jemalloc
它被用于火狐，安卓和其他一些应用程序中
it's also used in in Firefox Android a couple of other applications
Windows也有几种不同的堆实现
Windows has several different heap implementations as well and then
内核中有很多自定义的
there's a bunch of custom ones in kernel and so forth
这个有很多不同的实现
there's quite a lot of different implementations of this
到处都是
all over the place
但在本课程中，我们专注于Linux
but in this course we focus on Linux
我们将特别关注ptmalloc
and we're going to focus on ptmalloc specifically
但是我们讨论的很多概念
but a lot of the concepts that we discuss
对其它种类的动态分配器都适用
will be ??? across other dynamic allocators
我一直在说heap, 这个词到底是从哪里来的
i keep saying the heap where the heck did this word come from
实际上还不清楚
it's actually unclear
我尝试追踪堆这个词的历史使用情况
i try to track down a historic usage of the heap
它被称为堆，和有相同名字的堆数据结构没关系
it is not called the heap because of the similarly named data structure
堆实际是一个
the heap is an actual
堆是计算机科学中的一种数据结构
a heap is an actual data structure in computer science
我们说的不是这个
that's not what we're talking about
我们说的是一堆东西的堆
what we're talking about is more of usage in the sense of a heap of stuff like a pile the heap
不管出于什么原因
for whatever reason
由动态分配器管理的内存空间
the memory space that's managed by dynamic allocator
俗称堆
is colloquially known as the heap
从这节课开始，我很少会说动态分配器
and i think from here on in this module i'll rarely say dynamic allocator
一般会说堆
probably say heap
好吧
all right
这个堆做了什么？
so what does the heap do
根据dlmalloc和ptmalloc等实现的
as implemented by really dlmalloc and then now ptmalloc and all of its analogs
堆提供
the heap provides
实际上，如果了解一下malloc的历史
and actually if we wanted to go into kind of the the ancient history of malloc
可以看首个讲c的书《c programming language》
the first book on c the c programming language
我们搜索一下
let's pull it up
书里实际上有一个200行的malloc
the c programming language actually included a 200 line version of malloc
这是C语言的创造者写的书
this was the book written by the creators of C
它被称为K&R书
it's known as the K&R book
你应该考虑去看看
you should consider checking it out
维基百科上都有一篇关于它的文章
there's a Wikipedia article it's that important
它出版于1978年
and it was published in 1978
9年后
and then nine years later
dlmalloc出现了
dlmalloc came on to the scene
接口非常类似
i think with a very similar interface
哦，好的
oops all right
接口有malloc，free等
so the interface to allocators is malloc free right
使用malloc来获取一块内存
use malloc to get a chunk of memory to use
用free归还内存
use free to give it back
还有一些辅助函数比如realloc
there are also some auxiliary functions realloc
之前分配了这块内存
you say hey i had this previous allocation
能把它弄大点吗
can you please make it bigger
Calloc也是一个辅助函数
calloc is a helper function
它将分配内存并将其归零
that will allocate and zero out the memory right
正如在内存错误中讲过的
so as we talked about in memory errors
未初始化数据可能导致数据泄露等等
uninitialize data can lead to data disclosure and so forth
Calloc有助于防止这种情况
calloc helps guard against that
还有一些其他的接口，取决于你用的是什么
there are a couple of other ones depending on what you're using
例如，ptmalloc有一个叫做realloc数组的东西
for example ptmalloc has something called realloc array
它是realloc的高级版本
which is a fancier version of realloc
但这里最常用的是malloc和free
but for the most part the relevant things are malloc and free here
当然，其他因素也会起作用
and then the others of course also come into play
基本上只要不是hello world的程序
and basically every single program that is not hello world
甚至在很多情况下即使是hello world
and even in many cases hello world
都会使用堆
uses the heap
这是软件积木中最重要的部分之一
This is one of the most important parts of the building blocks of software
C + +程序使用这个功能
c plus plus programs behind the scenes use this functionality
Scanf和printf使用这个功能
scanf and printf behind the scenes use this functionality
任何中等复杂程度的程序都可能使用这个功能
and likely any moderately complex program uses this functionality
好吧
alright
堆是如何工作的
how does the heap work
这是个好问题
this is a good question
开头我们假设的堆实现
our hypothetical dynamic allocator implementation from the beginning of this lecture
通过
worked by
mmap然后把它获得的分成小块
memory mapping something and then splitting off chunks of it
有趣的是，ptmalloc不使用mmap
interestingly ptmalloc does not use mmap
它使用所谓的数据段
it uses what is called the data segment
数据段是一个历史上的怪东西，可以追溯到很久很久以前
data segment is a historical oddity back from the the old old old times
在AMD 64以前
Pre AMD 64
在X86以前
Pre modern usage of X86
即使内存空间被分了很多段
even when memory space was heavily segmented
还是有个数据的专属段
and you had a segment just for data
现在已经
nowadays this has been kind of
使用现代内存替代技术将其纳入堆中
coopted into the heap with modern memory replacement techniques
特别是加入了地址空间布局随机化
specifically with address space layout randomization
数据段随机放置在
the data segment is placed randomly
某个近似但不是绝对固定的偏移值
somewhere near but not actually right up against not a constant offset of
它就在位置无关二进制的基址附近
it's just somewhere near the base of a position independent binary
它从大小为0开始
it starts out with a size of zero
所以它实际上不会一开始显示在你的进程内存映射图上
so it doesn't actually show up on your processes memory map
它由两个系统调用管理
and it's managed by two system calls
一个系统调用是SBRK
one system call is sbrk
当你传递null给它时
which returns when you pass null to it
它返回数据段的当前末尾
it returns the current end of the data segment
如果你传递一个数字给它
if you pass a number to it
它就把数据段增加那么多字节
it shifts the data segment by that many bytes
另一个是BRK
and another one is brk which is
如果你输入一个地址
if you pass in an address
它将把数据段的末尾扩展到该地址
it'll expand the end of the data segment to that address
或者也可能缩小到这个地址
or probably shrink it as well
本质上
under the hood
这些是对内核的内存调用
so these are memory calls into the kernel
不是内存调用
not memory calls
系统调用
system calls into the kernel
当然，本质上和mmap一样
under the hood of course this all works just like mmap
内核映射内存，把它放在合适的位置，等等
the kernel maps memory puts it in places and so forth
不是很清楚
it's not exactly clear
为什么堆实现不直接使用mmap
why the heap implementations don't just use mmap
至少从安全的角度来看，我不太清楚
at least not exactly clear to me from a security perspective
很明显这不是很重要
and obviously it's not so relevant
但这是一个有趣的奇怪现象
but it's just an interesting oddity
就是还有另一种管理内存的方法
that there's yet another way to manage memory
让我们快速查看一下数据段
let's take a quick look at the data segment
它是如何在用户空间工作的
how it works from user space
我们来创建一个新函数
let's just create a new function
一个新程序
a new program
你要做的是malloc 16字节。
okay so what are you going to do is malloc sixteen.
就是这样
that's it
只要malloc 16字节
just malloc 16 bytes
如果我们编译这个
if we compile this
运行它，很明显它什么都没做，strace一下
all right run it obviously it does nothing but let's strace it
事情是这样的
here's what happens
好吧
alright
如果我们仔细看
if we look through
它都调用了哪些系统调用
what the system calls it makes
在这里
here
我们来做一下
actually let's do this
"马上要malloc"
about to malloc
我们输出一下我们要malloc了
we want to say that we're about to malloc
这样我们就能看到数据段何时被设置好
and then we'll be able to see  when the data segment get set up
好了,那么
alright so
对不起，我应该早点准备这个的
sorry i should have gotten this
应该早点把这个设置好
should have set this up earlier
想着临场发挥，这绝不是个好主意
i decided to go off script that is never a good idea
好了，这里我们输出 要malloc了
all right here we say about to malloc
我们输出到标准输出
let's just write to standard out
消息
the message
与消息的长度
with the length of message
我不用puts的原因是
the reason i'm removing puts is
puts有可能在内部使用malloc
it's possible that puts uses malloc internally
我想捕捉malloc首次使用的场景
i want to catch the first use of malloc
这样你就可以看到数据段的设置过程
so that you can see the data segment being set up
好了，我们开始，你看，这就是发生的事
alright here we go you see and that's what was happening in fact
我们输出了"要malloc了"
so we've wrote about to malloc
好吧
all right
很好，这是它的输出，然后调用malloc
that's great here's the output of that and then it mallocs and
这是在libc中第一次使用堆
the first time the heap is used in libc
完成数据段的设置
the data segment is set up
这里它首先调用SBRK
so here we have it first calls sbrk
我不知道strace为什么会搞砸
i'm not sure why strace screws this up
可能背后有什么疯狂的事
it could be something crazy under the hood
这是很有可能的
that's very possible
现在想起来可能是这样
it could be that now that i think about it maybe
SBRK可能是一个库包装器，而不是系统调用
sbrk is a library wrapper and not a system call
这两个系统调用都不属于
both of these system calls are not part of
Linux试图遵循的那种Unix标准，称为POSIX
the kind of Unix standard that Linux tries to follow called POSIX
它们曾经是，但后来被去掉了
they used to be but then they were taken out
所以世事无常
so things can vary
所以很有可能它们是一样的
so it's very possible that actually these are the same
不管怎样，当传入null时
sys... well anyways when passed in with null
如我所说，它返回数据段当前末尾地址
it returns the address of the current end address of the data segment as i said
它从0开始
it starts out at zero size
然后它说好的
and then it says okay well
让我们在数据段中分配一些空间
let's allocate some amount of space in the data segment
它会增加末尾地址的值
and it cause it with some increased value
我们可以在ipython中看看
and we can actually jump into ipython
然后把值打印出来
and print out what this
实际上这是那个较小的值
actually that's gonna be the lower value
与栈不同的数据段向右正常增长（地址值从低到高）
the data segment unlike the stack grows normally to the right
新地址减去旧地址
the new address minus the old address
这就是它分配的数量
this is exactly how much it allocates
十六进制21000
hex 21 000
这是它分配的21页内存
that is 21 pages of memory that it just allocates
在第一次使用堆时
the first time you use the heap
如果我们能看到的话
um we can actually if we can see
不是/flag
not slash flag
如果你查看/proc/self/maps文件
if you look at proc self maps
这将读出分配前后的映射
so this will read out the mapping before and after the allocation
再次strace，这是分配之前
as trace it again so here this is before the allocation
您可以看到数据段和libc之间没有任何内容
you can see there is nothing between the data segment and libc
还没有堆
there's no heap yet
然后发生了这两个BRK调用
then this occurs these two brk calls
现在我们有了堆
and now we have the heap
这个堆正好是
and that heap is exactly
从BRK返回的第一个地址
from the first address that was returned by brk
842000到863000
842000 to this 863000 right here
好了，这就是堆
alright so that is the heap
如果我们尝试分配比数据段中可用的更多的数据呢
now what if we try to allocate more than is available in the data segment
假如有
so let's say there is what
有20000或2个10000
there's 20000 or 2 10000
如果我们分配30000呢
what if we allocate 30000
和
and
是的，所以如果我们
yeah so if we
让我们用GCC。strace
let's gcc it. strace
这里
so here
这是我们分配大量内存的地方
this is where we're allocating our large amount of memory
可以看到，堆被扩展，以适应内存分配请求
and we can see that the heap is actually being expanded to fit all that allocation
ptmalloc是一个简洁的库
so basically ptmalloc is a neat library
它是开源的，显然你可以
it's open source you can obviously
你可以去查一下，读一读
you can go look it up and read it
大概有三五千行代码
it's something like three or five thousand lines of code
它主要帮你分配内存
and it is what does allocation for you
顺便说一下，如果你想分配巨大的内存
by the way if you try to allocate gigantic things
它不会使用数据段之类的
rather than using data segments and so forth
它会直接使用mmap，这很简洁
it'll just use mmap which is pretty neat
好的
all right so
堆有什么危险
what are the dangerous of the heap
这是个好问题
it's a good question
抱歉，技术故障
sorry technical glitch um
堆的危险是什么
what are the dangers of the heap
问题当然是
the problem is of course
堆是由不完美的程序员使用的
the heap is used by imperfect human programmers right
安全问题的首要原因是人类
the number one cause of security issues are humans
人类会忘记释放内存
humans will forget to free memory
人们会忘记指向已分配内存的指针存在哪里
humans will forget where they've stored pointers to memory they've allocated
人类会忘记他们释放了哪块内存
humans will forget what they freed
就在他们记得明明释放内存的时候
right when they do remember to free memory
再加上
and that coupled with
堆分配器对性能的追求几乎高于一切
the fact that the heap allocators strive for performance almost above all else
他们需要速度快
they need to be fast
对，因为
right because it's
可能性能对使用它们的程序至关重要
the programs that use them could be performance critical
例如
for example
可能有一个电子游戏，它使用了很多动态分配器
you could have a video game that uses dynamic allocators a lot
这个电子游戏需要运行得快
and that video game needs to run fast
所以你的动态分配器需要很快
and so your dynamic allocator needs to be fast
所以问题是，把重点放在优化上
so the problem is that with a massive focus on optimization
安全就经常被遗忘
securities often left behind
这就导致第一个问题
and this leads to issues caused by number one
与第二个问题结合起来就会成为了安全问题
becoming security issues when combined with number two
好吧
all right
我们如何发现用堆产生的问题和bug
how do we detect problems bugs that we make with the heap
在它们成为问题之前
before they become issues
有几种方法
there are a couple of ways
一个是内存执行分析工具valgrind
one is there's a memory execution analysis tool called valgrind
如果有能触发某些问题的测试用例
if you have test cases that trigger some problem
例如，一个非常常见的问题是您忘记释放内存
for example a very common problem is you forget to free memory
耗尽了资源
so you run out of resources
如果你有一个触发它的测试用例
if you have a test cases that trigger that
Valgrind经常可以
valgrind can often
当您通过valgrind执行这些测试用例时
when you execute those test cases through valgrind
它可以找到错误
it can find the error
Glibc本身有一些技术
glibc itself has some hardening techniques
您可以设置一些全局变量
there are global variables you can set
使堆更具防御性
to make the heap a little more defensive oriented
其中很多会影响性能
a lot of these will tank performance
尤其是这个
especially this one
这使得所有分配都通过mmap完成
this one makes all allocations being be done through mmap
但其中一些是
but some of these are are
其中很多还是可以绕过的
and a lot of these can still be bypassed
没有万能的办法
there's no silver bullet
还有很多更安全的分配器已经被开发出来了
and then there are a lot of kind of more secure allocators that have been developed
但总的来说
but in general
它们还没有真正投入使用
they haven't really been deployed
它们通常比我们熟悉和喜爱的分配器慢得多
they're usually much slower than the allocators that we know and love
总的来说，没有通用的技术被创造出来
and in general no generic technique has been created
用来检测这些错误
for detecting these sorts of errors
这与检测其他类型的错误是一个类似的主题
and this is a similar theme to detecting other types of errors
所以问题很严重
so problems are pretty serious
在这个模块中，我们会讨论很多这样的问题
in this module we'll go through a lot of these problems
呃
uh
从稍微深入一点的危险类型开始
starting with a slightly deeper dive into the types of dangers
然后进入实际的实现细节
and then going into actual implementations specifics
我希望你能玩得开心
i hope you will have fun with this one